Okay, so this is the promised video
about how pattern-matching drives
lazy evaluation in Haskell.
And you should probably watch this while
having the slides at slide 146 open.
Because there I have the function
definitions I'm going to use.
So, I will not repeat them here,
but they are on that slide.
And what's also on the slide is this
expression I think that I wanted to evaluate.
And well, let's go about this.
Okay, so you have a definition of f
and you know what head and tail are.
Now, how do we evaluate this?
Well, you could say, well, let's
simply evaluate this 3 + 1 to 4.
But that would be wrong.
Because we only want to evaluate on demand.
You only want to evaluate things
that are needed, actually.
And we can't tell this now upfront that
this will be eventually needed, this 4.
Because maybe this 'f' discards that element.
And then we shouldn't compute 3 + 1 is
4 if we are not going to use the thing.
So, how do we instead proceed?
Well, we have to see what we have to know in
order to know what the outcome of this is.
Well, we have to know what head of something is.
And we can't do this without having
computed this something at least as
far as being able to tell what the head is, okay.
So, that's why we need to go inside.
Well, we can only compute the
tail of something if we at least
know whether that something
is the empty list or not.
So, we will have to compute
this 'f' of that list.
Now if you look at the slide, the
definition of 'f' then it's defined by
case distinctions by pattern-matching on
the empty list or the non-empty list.
Right?
So, it doesn't have a case for two element lists,
but it has this case with the empty list or with
the cons constructor (':')
between some variables x and xs.
Okay, so how do we proceed then here?
Well, we should keep in mind what
this list is actually represented like,
namely as something like this, right?
In this list view of data constructors.
And then if you look at the definition
of f, then there's a case for x : xs.
So, this will be x and this will be xs.
So, inside this head and tail context, we use
the right-hand side of the second 'f' equation.
And what that then means is that we
should apply 'g' to x, so to this 3,
and have cons (':') and 'f'
applied to the rest of the list.
Right to this list.
And again, we don't evaluate
the 3 + 1 to 4 at this point.
Because we are not yet certain
that this will actually be needed.
So, this is the next expression
that you should look at.
Okay, then we again have to see
what do we have to compute where
we want head of something, so we should
know what the head of the thing is.
We should see the data constructor
for the non-empty list.
So, we can't yet compute the head.
We have to compute the thing
which appears nested inside.
Okay, should we maybe now compute g 3?
No, we shouldn't.
Because the tail will
actually just cut this part.
So, the tail of a non-empty list
is the remainder of that list.
So, yes, similarly to the head definition
the tail definition would look like this.
So, this x is not used.
So, we shouldn't compute the g 3, that
would be a superfluous computation.
That wouldn't be lazy, but we want to be lazy.
Okay, so instead, the tail of
something rest list is the rest list.
So, at this point, we will simply project
to this 'f' of this singleton list.
So, this is the next step.
Not computing this.
Okay, so g 3 will never be computed.
Okay, so we have the head of something again,
we can't yet compute the head, we have to
compute the thing inside these brackets.
Now, what is this?
This is an 'f' call, it's not the empty list.
It's basically 'f' on this.
So, again, the second equation of 'f' will apply.
And what does it do?
Well, inside this context, of course,
we get a 'g' call on the first argument
on the first element of that list.
And again, we don't compute
the 3 + 1 at this point,
because it's not yet clear
that we will need this.
And what is the remainder of this call?
Well, it is 'f' applied to the rest list, and
well, the rest list here is the second argument.
It's the empty list.
Okay, now we can actually compute
the head because now inside the
argument position of the head, we really have
something of the form head element rest list.
Okay, so this now reduces to g (3 + 1).
And again, we didn't compute
the 'f' of the empty list.
This will, of course, be the empty list.
But we don't compute this at this point.
Because this is discarded by the head function;
we don't compute some subexpressions
that are not going to be needed.
And what's going to be needed
comes out via pattern-matching.
Okay, so we have this.
Now we have to compute the 3 + 1,
because if you look at the definition of
g on the slide, then you'll see
that it does a pattern-matching.
So, we have to know: Is this first
argument some certain constant that
appears in the first occasion of the g function?
Okay, in order to decide this, we have
to actually now compute this value.
Okay, so now we compute g 4.
Well, we reduced this to 4.
So, now we have to compute g 4.
Okay, look, again, at the definition
of g, it tests two cases.
The first case doesn't match
here, because we have a different
constant number in the first case of
the 'g' call of the 'g' definition.
So, we have to apply the second one
and the second one is g n is n + 1.
Okay, so now it is,
of course, the four,
so this reduces to 4 + 1.
And then we get 5.
Okay, so of course, you would have got the same
if you had simply put this into the interpreter.
But now you also see what essentially the kind of
steps the interpreter will do
in evaluating this 5 here.
And most importantly, you will also
see which parts are not computed.
Or when they are computed.
So, this is not computed upfront; it's only
computed when we realize that we actually need it.
And some things are never computed.
g 3 is never computed.
And the empty list is also not computed.
Okay.
Plus, you also need this perspective in order
to be able to match some arguments like this.
Okay, and the same kind of
example and derivation/evaluation
applies to all Haskell evaluation,
to all Haskell programs.